Register of the Ol'ga Tissarevskaia Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Ol'ga Tissarevskaia papers
1895-1980
2000C111
Hoover Institution Archives
1 microfilm reel (0.15 linear feet)
Correspondence, speeches and writings, personal documents, printed matter, and photographs, relating to Russian émigré affairs.
Tissarevskaia, Olga, 1895-
Access
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2000.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Location of Originals
Originals in: Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco.
Biography
Olga Tissarevskaia was born Ol'ga Petrovna Krasnova on 28 September 1895 (O.S.) in the village of Bogdanovka, near Samara, Russia. In 1921, she emigrated to Poland with her husband, an engineer named Viacheslav Doubrava, and ran a boarding house until the Second World War. Doubrava died in the mid-1920s, and Olga married a former colonel named Georgii Tissarevskii.
Coming to the United States in 1949, she worked for a brief period as a housekeeper to the Swedish ambassdor to the U.S., but through intelligent real estate investments soon achieved financial independence for herself and her already ill husband (who died in 1965). Living in retirement in Phoenix, Arizona, she gained recognition as a painter (specializing in oil paintings on silk), and also wrote for the émigré press, particularly Novoe russkoe slovo (where she published accounts of her travels). She was married again in the 1970s to a Russian named Nikolai Topalov. Her autobiography, Svet i teni moei zhizni, was published in Buenos Aires in 1973.
Chronology
1895 September 28 (O. S.) Born, Bogdanovka village, Samarskii uezd, Russia
1918 Left Russia for Poland
1973 Author, Svet i teni moei zhizni
Scope and Content Note
Ol'ga Tissarevskaia was a painter and journalist active in the Russian émigré press; she was noted primarily for her accounts of travel to exotic locales. The collection includes biographical information, a small number of her writings, including her memoirs, Svet i teni moei zhizni, and a large number of photographs (not filmed) of places she visited and people she met, as well as correspondence and miscellany from her travels.
Detailed processing and preservation microfilming for these materials were made possible by a generous grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and by matching funds from the Hoover Institution and Museum of Russian Culture. The grant also provides depositing a microfilm copy in the Hoover Institution Archives. The original materials remain in the Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco as its property. A transfer table indicating corresponding box and reel numbers is available at the Hoover Institution Archives.
The Hoover Institution assumes all responsibility for notifying users that they must comply with the copyright law of the United States (Title 17 United States Code) and Hoover Rules for the Use and Reproduction of Archival Materials.
Poland.; Russia.; Russians--Poland.; Russians--United States.; United States.
- Biographical File, 1895-1976 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Articles, birth certificate, clippings, employment records, passport, scrapbook and miscellany, arranged alphabetically by physical form
- Correspondence, 1949-1980 (Box 1-2)
  Letters and cards, arranged alphabetically by correspondent
- Speeches and Writings, 1972-1973 (Box 2)
  Articles and memoirs, with related correspondence and reviews, arranged chronologically by title
- Subject File, and., 1967-1969 undated (Box 2)
  Brochure, clippings and attached photograph, arranged alphabetically by heading
- Photographs, 1917-1977 (Box 3-4)
  Albums and individual postcards and photographs, primarily chronicling Tissarevskaia's world travel. Also includes photographs of her artwork, family members and three husbands. Arranged alphabetically by physical form. Not filmed
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1895-1976 (Box 1)
  - Articles about or mentioning Ol'ga Tissarevskaia (Folder 1: 1)
  - Birth certificate (Folder 1: 2)
  - Clippings about or mentioning Ol'ga Tissarevskaia (Folder 1: 3)
  - Educational records (Folder 1: 4)
  - Employment records. (Folder 1: 5)
    Includes letters of recommendation, vocational certificates and attached photographs
  - Family file - Topalov, Nikolai (husband). Diploma (Folder 1: 6)
  - Inventories of archive (Folder 1: 7)
  - Passports (Folder 1: 8)
  - Scrapbook (Folder 1: 9)
  - Miscellany. (Folder 1: 10)
    Includes business cards, clippings, receipts, signed menus, and other matter
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1949-1980
  - General, and, 1949-1980 undated (Folder 1: 11)
  - Bellavina, Nonna, undated (Folder 1: 12)
    Includes attached photograph of Nonna Bellavina and unidentified individuals
  - Brandt, Kirill and Mariia, and, 1971 undated (Folder 1: 13)
  - Karateev, Mikhail (Karachevskii-Karateev, Mikhail, Prince), 1971-1978 (Folder 1: 14)
  - Meyer, George (Meier, Iurii Konstantinovich), and, 1979 undated (Folder 1: 15)
  - Pesqueira, Holda and Victor, and., 1968-1972 undated (Box-folder 2: 1)
    General note
    See also SUBJECT FILE
    Includes attached photograph.
  - Tolstaia, Aleksandra L'vovna, 1971-1973 (Folder 2: 2)
    See also SUBJECT FILE/Tolstoy family
  - Votichenko, Sacha, 1971 (Folder 2: 3)
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1972-1973
  - "Kumys v Rossii," Novoe russkoe slovo, 1972 February 26 (Folder 2: 4)
    Printed copy
  - "V shestoi raz vokrug sveta," Novoe russkoe slovo, 1972 April 24-28 (Folder 2: 5)
  - Svet i teni moei zhizni, 1973
    - Correspondence relating to the book's publication in English, 1972 (Folder 2: 6)
    - Printed copy (Folder 2: 7)
    - Reviews (Folder 2: 8)
- SUBJECT FILE, and., 1967-1969 undated
  Brochure, clippings and photograph
  - Kovacevic, Branko. (Folder 2: 9)
    Includes biographical information and photograph of Kovacevic with Tissarevskaia
  - Pesqueira, Victor M. (Folder 2: 10)
    Clippings
  - Tolstoy family. (Folder 2: 11)
    Reminiscences of her father, Leo Tolstoy, by Alexandra Tolstoy, published in TV Guide
- PHOTOGRAPHS, 1917-1977 (Box 3)
  Albums and individual photographs, primarily chronicling Tissarevskaia's world travel. Also includes photographs of her artwork, family members and three husbands. Not filmed
  - Albums (Folder 3: 1-4)
  - Albums (Box-folder 4: 1-3)
  - Postcards and photographs of miscellaneous people and places (Folder 4: 5)